Guide to the Alexander Ivanovitch Petrunkevitch Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alexander Ivanovitch Petrunkevitch papers
1886-1964
MS 394
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
The papers consist primarily of Alexander Petrunkevitch's personal correspondence and contain numerous letters from his father Ivan Il'ich Petrunkevitch and stepmother Anastasia Petrunkevitch. These letters include discussions of the Russian political climate (1900-1919) and focus on Ivan Petrunkevitch's work with the Constitutional Democratic (Kadety) Party. Other correspondents include officials of Russian-American societies. The papers also encompass Alexander Petrunkevitch's writings on the Russian Revolution, his poetry, journals, photographs, and other personal memorabilia.
Petrunkevitch, Alexander, 1875-1964
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Papers in part purchased from the family in 1965 and in part transferred from the Yale Biology Department, 1979; gift of Edward Opton, 2002.
Existence and Location of Copies
Correspondence of Ivan and Alexander Petrunkevitch is also available on microfilm (1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM70.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, 1886-1963. II. Writings, 1917-1963. III. Personal Papers and Photographs, 1894-1964.
Biographical / Historical
Alexander Petrunkevitch was born in Pliski, Russia in 1875 and taught at the University of Moscow before immigrating to Germany to escape political persecution. He earned a Ph.D. at the University of Freiburg in 1901. Petrunkevitch taught biology at Harvard University and the University of Indiana before joining the Yale University faculty in 1910. He was known for his research on spiders. He died in New Haven, Connecticut on March 10, 1964.
Scope and Contents
The Alexander Ivanovitch Petrunkevitch Papers consist of correspondence, writings, personal memorabilia, and photographs which relate to Petrunkevitch's family and his interests in Russia, particularly the Russian revolution. The papers contain numerous letters from Petrunkevitch's father Ivan Il'ich Petrunkevitch and his stepmother Anastasia Petrunkevitch which focus on their years in exile in Crimea and, after the 1905 revolution, the work of the Constitutional Democratic Party. The papers contain no materials on Alexander Petrunkevitch's teaching career or his research on arachnids.
The papers are arranged in three series: I. CORRESPONDENCE, 1886-1963 II. WRITINGS, 1917-1963 III. PERSONAL PAPERS AND PHOTOGRAPHS, 1894-1964
Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, contains Petrunkevitch's correspondence with family members and with Russian friends and associates. Most of the letters are in Russian, with lesser quantities in English and German. The letters in the "General" folders are arranged in chronological order; the bulk of the material dates from 1919 to 1924. Petrunkevitch's commitment to furthering American-Russian cooperation is reflected in his letters as president of the Russian Collegiate Institute beginning in 1917 and as a member of the Inter-Racial Council beginning in 1919. Correspondence with August Weismann, Petrunkevitch's mentor at the University of Freiburg, is in folder 38.
The bulk of the series, however, is composed of Petrunkevitch's letters from his father and stepmother Ivan Il'ich and Anastasia Petrunkevitch. The letters commence when Alexander Petrunkevitch leaves home as a young student in 1886. By 1899 when Petrunkevitch was studying in Germany there are monthly letters. Ivan Petrunkevitch's lengthy letters from Tver concern his involvement in the Zemski Sobor, while his stepmother, who signs herself Nastia, writes of family matters. Letters from 1904 to 1911 are written from Crimea and contain observations of Tatar life and customs. Though Ivan Petrunkevitch was elected as a delegate from Crimea to the first Duma in 1905, there are few contemporary letters to document this period. Letters from 1919 on, however, when Ivan Petrunkevitch was engaged in writing his memoirs, contain extensive reflections on the 1905 Revolution, the Constitutional Democratic Party, and the political climate through 1918. Following the Bolshevik Revolution the Petrunkevitchs fled Russia and eventually settled in Prague (1924). Letters from Prague reflect Ivan Petrunkevitch's interest in the democratic experiment of T.G. Masaryk's government.
Series II, WRITINGS, consists of Alexander Petrunkevitch's addresses, articles, book reviews, and poetry. Most of Petrunkevitch's articles concern Russia, particularly the political climate before, during, and after the October Revolution. Petrunkevitch's Russian poetry is in the romantic tradition and narrates tales of tragic love.
Petrunkevitch's personal papers and photographs comprise Series III. The series includes memorabilia such as family history, certificates, awards, and diplomas and files which document Petrunkevitch's interests in Russian organizations in America. Petrunkevitch's journals contain personal reflections as well as additional examples of his poetry. Petrunkevitch published some of these Russian poems under his pseudonym A. Jon-Ruban in Leipzig in 1900. Photographs of Petrunkevitch, his family, friends, and the Russian countryside are in folders 75-79 and 85-87. The photograph album for 1903 (folder 75) contains pictures taken on Petrunkevitch's return visit to Pliski with his American wife.
Exiles; Europe -- Description and travel; Krymskai︠a︡ oblastʹ (Ukraine) -- Social life and customs; Prague (Czech Republic) -- Politics and government; Russia -- Politics and government -- 1894-1917; Russia -- History -- Nicholas II, 1894-1917; Photoprints; Arachnologists; Poets; Zoologists; Petrunkevitch, Alexander, 1875-1964; Petrunkevitch, Anastasia; Petrunkevitch, Ivan Il'ich, 1843-1928; Konstitut͡sionno-demokraticheskai͡a partii͡a; Russian Collegiate Institute (New York, N.Y.)
- Correspondence, 1886-1963; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  General correspondence (folders 1-14) is arranged in chronological order. The remainder of the series is organized in alphabetical order by correspondents' names.
  - General, 1901-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
  - Petrunkevitch, I. I, 1886-1920 (Box 1, Folder 15-21)
  - Petrunkevitch, I. I., 1921-1928 (Box 2, Folder 22-31)
  - Petrunkevitch, Anastasia (Nastia), 1888-1932 (Box 2, Folder 32-36)
  - Petrunkevitch family and friends, 1893-1932 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Weismann, August, 1899-1914 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Fragments, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Writings, 1917-1963; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  This series is arranged alphabetically by record type. Articles are in alphabetical order by title. Untitled short manuscripts are organized by subject.
  - Addresses and memoranda, 1917-1948 (Box 3, Folder 40-41)
  - Articles
    - "Americanization and Peace", Undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "August Weismann: Personal Reminiscences", 1963 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - "Influences of Russian Political Parties, The", [ca. 1918] (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - "Political Crisis in Russia", 1917 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "Role of the Intellectuals in the Liberating Movements in Russia", undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - "Russia and the Baltic States", 1923-1924 (Box 3, Folder 47-48)
    - "Russia Before the War", Undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - "Russia Recovering", Undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "Russian Revolution, The", Undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - "Sketches From Russian Life", Undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - "Truth About Rasputin, The", Undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "Universities in the United States", Undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Bolshevism, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Book reviews, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Poetry, 1917; 1945; undated (Box 3, Folder 57-59)
    General
    See also: box 4, folders 63-67
  - Russia and change, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
- Personal papers and photographs, 1894-1964; Series III
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by subject and record type.
  - Clippings, 1917, 1922, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Family genealogy, Undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Journals, 1894 - [irca 1924] (Box 4, Folder 63-67)
  - Jubilee in honor of A. I. Petrunkevitch, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 68-69)
  - Manual Slavonic Personalities, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Memorabilia
    - Awards, certificates, and diplomas, 1894-1906 (Box 5, Folder 71)
      See also: box 7, folder 90
    - Honorarium, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 72)
      See also: box 7, folder 88
    - Miscellaneous, 1918-1964 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Novikov, M.M. Ot Moskvy do Niu-Iorka ( From Moscow to New York ), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Photograph album, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Photograph albums, Undated (Box 6, Folder 76-77)
  - Photographs, 1895-1919 (Box 6, Folder 78-79)
    See also: box 7, folder 89
    See also:box 7, folders 85-87
  - Poetry, undated (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Russian Collegiate Institute, undated (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Russian committees, undated (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Russian Orthodox Church, 1922-1927 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Svidetelstvo (Lineage), 1894 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Oversize
    - Photographs, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 85-87)
    - Honorarium, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Awards, certificates, and diplomas, 1901; 1906; 1927 (Box 7, Folder 90)